All right, let's get started. So, um,
first thing I'm going to do is put my
name and then description. I'm going to
say computer
uses algorithm to guess
numbers from the user. All right, so we
want to write a program. Um, we want to
welcome the user to the game. So, we'll
just say alert,
welcome to the computer guessing game.
The computer will guess a number from
your head. K.
Um, then we're going to prompt them for
the maximum number in the range. Um, so
I'm going to need to store the maximum
number. So I'm going to say let maxum
equals, we'll initialize it to zero, but
we'll change it later. We'll say minum
equals zero. Um, we're going to need the
minimum number.
Um,
we're going to need a number for the
computer guess.
Um,
we're going to need a string for the
user response.
And let's see.
We're going to need a running number of
guesses. So, let num guesses equal zero.
So, what I've done is I've created all
of my variables ahead of time. Um, so
I'm going to create a little comment up
here says
variables needed for the program
and we initialize them as well.
Okay, then I'm going to welcome them to
the program. Now I need them to provide
me a maximum number in the range. Um,
that number is going to need to be a
number. So we're going to convert it.
Um, so let's say let max num or sorry
we've already created the maximum number
variable. So we'll say max num equals
and then we'll convert whatever the user
gives us into an integer and we'll
prompt them
and say um what is the maximum
number in your range
and then we'll convert that into an
integer and we'll store it
Um
then we'll say what is the minimum
number in your range. So we'll say min
num equals and I'm actually going to
copy this
and paste it and I'm going to just
change the word maximum to minimum.
Okay. So now we've gathered the maximum
number and the minimum number. Now we
need to alert them the game is starting.
The game has begun.
Now, we need to have the computer guess
the middle number in the current range.
So, let's think through this
mathematically. Um, if the if your range
was from 50 to 100, um, then the number
halfway would be the distance between
them divided by two. And so, the
distance between 50 and 100 is 50
divided by two is 25. So 25 above 50 or
25 below 100 is going to give us the
middle of the range. Middle of that
range is going to be 75. So from the
steps that I just took as I thought
through it, I took the maximum number in
the range and the min and subtracted off
the minimum number of the range to
figure out the distance. Then once I
figured out the distance, I took that
distance and added it to the minimum
number of the range to get to the middle
of the range. So I'm going to do that
now in code. Now that I've thought
through how I want to do that. So here
I'm going to say um take
um the distance is going to be the
maximum number minus the minimum number
um and then we'll divide it by two. So
we'll say maximum number minus minimum
number and that is the distance. So, I'm
say let distance equal maximum number
minus minimum number. Because I'm trying
to make all of my variables be up here
at the top, I'm actually going to remove
that and I'm going to say let distance
equals zero. Then down here, I'm going
to reuse the distance variable. I'm
going to set it equal to the maximum
number minus the minimum number. So,
that gives me the distance between them.
Halfway is going to be that distance
divided by two. Um,
and so the guess is going to be um the
distance / 2. And then once I figured
out what that is, I'm going to add it to
the minimum number. So going through
this again,
100 is the maximum number minus the
minimum number of 50 gives us 50.
And then we're going to take 50 and
divide it by 2, which gives us 25. And
then we're going to add that to the
minimum number, which was 50. So 50 + 25
is 75. And thus our guess is now exactly
in the middle. Now that we've made that
guess, um, we need to prompt the user to
see if it's correct.
So, we'll say um user response equals
prompt
the computer and actually I'm going to
use a formatted string here.
Say the computer
guessed the number
and then we're going to enter our guess
here. So guess that number.
Is that correct? Enter C for correct,
H for too high,
and L for too low.
And then um down below it says make sure
to normalize your input. Adjust to
handle both capital C and lowerase C.
The way you do that is you say dot to
lowercase. That converts everything to
lowerase. So if they enter a capital C,
it'll be a lowercase C. If they enter a
lowerase C, it'll be a capital C. Um
based on the user's response, adjust the
range accordingly. So what we're going
to do is we're going to say um if
um user response
is h
then that means they guessed too high.
So if they guess too high the new
maximum becomes whatever the computer
guessed last. So what we're going to do
is we're going to say
um max num equals guess
else if user response
is um l
if it's too low the new minimum becomes
whatever the computer guessed. So we'll
say max
or sorry minum
equals guess
and then finally
we'll say else if
user response
is correct.
Um
then we'll set both the min num equal to
the guess and the max num equal to the
guess.
And then we'll have an else here and
we'll just alert
not a valid response.
Okay.
Then it says repeat the process of
guessing the middle number and adjusting
the range until the computer gets the
correct number.
So we need to repeat the process from
five all the way to seven and we need to
keep doing it until the computer gets
the right number. So in other words,
while the guess is not the same as the
user's enter number, then um
we need to run the guess again. So to do
that, let's do a while loop. So we'll
have and as a matter of fact we always
want to make at least one guess. So
we're going to do a dowh loop. So
once we've alerted that the game has
begun we're going to say do
and then we're going to go all the way
until the end of that if statement. And
then to format your code, you can hold
um altshift f or on a Mac it's option
shift f and that will format your code.
So I'm going to do this while
um the guess is not equal to um
the
sorry we're going to run this while the
user response is not equal to C because
if the user response is C then it's the
number from the user's head. If it's not
C then we need to run this loop again.
So, while the user response is not C,
figure out the distance between the
maximum number and the minimum number.
Guess the middle number, prompt them if
it's correct. If the user enters C, then
we know our range is correct and we'll
end the loop. If they didn't enter C,
then we're going to adjust our range and
adjust our range and run our loop again.
That means the only way we can get
outside of this loop is if we've guessed
the correct number. So, what we want to
do is now we want to um so it says
repeat the process of guessing the
middle number and adjusting the range
until the computer gets the correct
number. Once the computer guesses the
number, display the number of attempts
it took. Well, we actually haven't been
tracking attempts thus far. Um what
we've done is we've alerted them. We've
created our range and then we've put in
two numbers and then we've guessed. And
so once we make this guess, we actually
probably want to increment the number of
guesses. So we set our number of guesses
to zero at the start. So right here, I'm
going to say
increment guesses
and we're going to take user response.
Sorry,
we're going to take the number of
guesses and we're going to increment it.
All right,
we've guessed their input. So now we can
alert
array. The computer guessed it.
It only took
numb guesses,
tries.
Okay, let's save this and let's go test
it. So, I'm going to go live
and it's going to say, "Welcome to the
computer guessing game. The computer
will guess a number from your head."
So, I'm going to go with 76.
So, what is the And I'll use the range 0
to 100. So, what is the maximum number
in your range? 100. What is the minimum
number in the range? We'll actually go
with one. So, it says the game has
begun. Um, the computer guessed the
number 50.5. Is that correct? Enter C
for correct, H for too high, and L for
too low. Well, my number was 76. So, I'm
going to say that that's too low. And
then it said it guessed 75.25.
Is that correct? It's still too low. And
then it guessed 87.625.
That's too high. Uh 81.4375.
That's too low. And this is probably
going to go on forever and ever and ever
because it's guessing decimal places and
I want it to guess whole numbers. So
what we're going to do is we're going to
go around that number. So let's come
over
here and instead of setting our guess
equal to the distance plus the minimum
number, we're going to round this. Um,
and the way we're going to do that is
we're going to say guess equals guess.2
to fixed.
And then it says, how many decimal
places do you want? I want zero decimal
places, but you'll notice this returns a
string. So, we're going to have to
convert this to a number. Um, I've been
using uh parse int and parse float. Um,
but you can also use the number function
and that will also convert it to a
number. So, we're going to take our
guess, round it to zero decimal places,
turn it into a number, and now we'll try
our code again. So, we'll hit cancel.
We'll reload the page. Um, we're going
to go with 76. What's the maximum number
in our range? 100. What's the minimum?
One. Game has begun. Uh, guessed 51. Is
that correct? That is too low. It
guessed 76. Is that correct? That is
correct. And it says, hooray. The
computer guessed it. It only took two
tries. And so, it looks like our code is
working. Let's come over and do some
cleaning up. Um, so
we've got our name and description.
We've got the variables needed. Um, we
probably don't need this comment
anymore. So, let's get rid of that. Um,
we welcome the user, ask them to provide
the number, display the alert, and then
here I'm going to add a comment that
says calculating
the mid guess.
And then here we're going to prompt them
and see if it's correct. The user should
respond with that. And then we're going
to increment the guess. We don't need
that anymore. We don't need that
anymore. Um, based on the response,
adjust the range accordingly. And then,
um, I'm going to
remove those. We don't need those
anymore.
Um,
and up above the dowhile loop, I'm going
to say keep guessing until you get it
right.
Until actually, until the computer gets
it right.
And then we're going to take this
comment and says once it does display
that, and we're just going to move it
above the alert. So now looks like we've
cleaned things up nicely. And our code
is good to go. Uh hopefully you were
able to come to a solution on your own.
This is my solution. Um and that
concludes this video. Thanks for
watching.